SIDRA FATIMA MINHAS

House No. 3 B, Block G, Gulberg III. Lahore. Pakistan Tel No.: +92(0)42-35838999 Mobile: +92 (0)3334989444 Email: sidra.minhas@gmail.com, sidra.minhasjehat@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Sound governance knowledge and skills. Good research skills (presentation and interpretation of data among others). Experience in management/administration; working with government departments and offices at the federal, provincial and district level. Effective report writing skills. Fluent speaker of English and Urdu.

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

- Result Based Project Management and M&E: Significant experience in management of development projects addressing education and health related issues with a specific focus on gender mainstreaming in the project cycle.
- Gender Expert and Researcher: Significant experience in research with strong skills in qualitative and quantitative analysis.
- Governance and Institutional Strengthening: Experience in governance and institutional development (including human resources and capacity issues). Experience of designing and conducting need assessment, situation analysis and evaluation studies.
- Communication and Report Writing: Experience of project report writing catering to both the internal (organizational) and external (donor) requirements; planning and development of communication strategy and tools.
- Trainer and Facilitator: Experienced workshop and training facilitator.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Project Officer, Canada-Pakistan Basic Education Project

May 2008 to June 2011

The aim of the Canada Pakistan Basic Education Project was to improve the quality and delivery of basic education in Pakistan, especially the female population, and increase access to education. Core responsibilities include:

- Develop and implement gender strategy for Project
- Conduct research on gender specific issues and publish and disseminate material to raise awareness
- Undertake training of partner staff for gender sensitization
- Participate in Working Groups meetings to ensure gender integration in revised models and materials
- Organize and manage events related to disseminating project learning, achievements, best practices and success stories relating to gender integration
- Preparation of Project progress reports, quarterly financial reports, annual work plan and budgets
- Ensure gender integration in all activities, ensure reporting reflects gender dimensions, and advise on specific questions related to gender issues

Research Associate, Canada-Pakistan Basic Education Project

December 2006 to April 2008

The Research Associate tasks included

- Technical and administrative assistance to Project Director, Technical Advisors and Consultants
- Coordinating with partner institutions in need analysis and capacity building activities
- Liaising with donors involved in the capacity building of institutions in the project
- Supporting data collection, analysis and synthesis and editing and writing reports
- Supporting consultative workshops

Financial Aid Officer, the Lahore University of Management Sciences,

May 2003-September 2004

- Worked under the guidance of the General Manager of the Department in managing the external funding aspect of the donors contributing scholarships and loans to students
- Managed work-study program of approximately five hundred students
- Assisted in identifying areas of improvement of Admissions Management System.

Intern, Muslim Commercial Bank (Pvt.) Ltd., Lahore, Pakistan

CONSULTANCIES

Consultant, Oxfam Great Britain Pakistan

June 2011

Documenting of case stories under a CIDA funded project in Neelam and Bagh Districts, Azad Jammu and Kashmir

Governance Sector Early Recovery and Rehabilitation Expert, UNDP

April to December 2011

Provide technical support to Sectoral Working Groups (SWGs) established by Early Recovering Working Group with co-chaired by respective Disaster Management Authority and UNDP.

Consultant, Save the Children

March to April 2011

Research Study on Teachers and Parents Assumptions about Education in a Primary Education Project in Battagram, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa

Team Lead, Insaan Dost Association (IDA)

March to July 2011

End of Project Evaluation for IDA for project on "Promotion and Protection of rights of bonded labourers" funded by Trocaire Ireland.

Associate Researcher, Semiotics/ILO

October to December 2010

Conducted a sector analysis of the hospitality sector in Pakistan through a gender lens.

Consultant, FIRMS – USAID

May to July 2010

Provide technical support Gender Specialist and Gender Advisor to build the capacity of government officials to mainstream gender in the (i) formulation, (ii) implementation, and (iii) monitoring and evaluation of government policies, plans, programmes and projects in all areas of development.

Consultant – Researcher (Maternal and Child Health Service Delivery and Capacity Building Providers), SNV Netherlands Development Organization

March to September 2010

Researcher, LCDF - Scaling Local Solutions, Capacity Development Services for the Health focusing on maternal and child health, Market Survey and Analysis

Consultant Editor Annual Magazine of the Management and Professional Development Department, Government of the Punjab, (MPDD), Asian Development Bank

May to July 2009

Technical support to develop and quality assurance of annual magazine of the Management and Professional Development Department, Government of the Punjab (MPDD) and training strategy for Punjab.

Consultant, Church World Service Afghanistan- Pakistan

December 2007 to June 2008

Conduct research on service delivery of government run shelter homes (Dar ul Amaans) and elucidate marginalization of women for a Project on Advocacy for Women in Shelter Homes in Lahore.

TRAININGS

Material Development Specialist and Facilitator/Trainer, National Institute of Disaster Management (NIDM) and Provincial Disaster Management Authority Punjab (PDMA-Punjab)

December 2010

Development of module on Gender focused Disaster Risk Reduction

Material Development Specialist and Facilitator/Trainer, Pakistan Association for Continuing and Adult Education (PACADE)

June 2010

Development of Gender Sensitization and HIV/AIDS module for workshop for Government School Teachers teaching grade 6-8 and conduct of workshop in Lahore for a UNESCO funded series of workshops.

Consultant, the Development Pool

March 2007 to date

Provide technical support to the firm on various projects.

➤ Material Development Specialist and Facilitator/Trainer, Agha Khan Foundation Pakistan February to May 2010

Development and Delivery of Training of Trainers (ToT) Module on Local Resource Mobilization /Social Entrepreneurship for Citizens' Community Boards

TEACHING AND FACILITATION EXPERIENCE

Visiting Faculty, Beaconhouse National University, Lahore

October 2010 to November 2010

Teaching a course on Methods in Qualitative Research to MA Education Leadership and Management Students

Visiting Faculty, University of the Punjab Lahore

September 2010 to date

Teaching a course on Women in Distress to Masters classes in the Department of Gender Studies

Visiting Faculty, Government College University Lahore

September 2006 to February 2007

Taught History of Feminism to MPhil

Teacher and Facilitator, The Lahore Grammar School

January 2002- October 2002

Teacher and Facilitator, American National School

February 2000 - August 2001

PUBLICATIONS

Minhas, S. F., Zahid, M. and Siddique, A. (2011), "Changa Paani: An Urban Water and Sanitation Solution – Early impacts and essential responses" - Poverty Alleviation Policy Papers Series Monograph No.5. Islamabad, Pakistan, Akhtar Hameed Khan Resource Center.

Minhas, S. F. (2009), "The Politics of Rape and Honor in Pakistan" in Cuklanz, L. and Moorti, S. (eds.) Local Violence, Global Media: Feminist Analysis of Gendered Representations. Peter Lang Publishing, New York.

REPORT

Minhas, S. F. and Sakurai, K. (2008), Marginalization, deprivation and disempowerment: 16 Pakistani women's journey to the Dar-ul-Amaan. Church World Service _ Pakistan and Afghanistan, Lahore.

NEWSLETTER ARTICLES

"Participatory Development in Gender" in CPBEP Newsletter for Canada Pakistan Basic Education Project Volume 1, No.2, Spring 2008. Semiotics Consultants (Pvt.) Limited.

Viewpoint: "Changes for Women and Girls in the wake of the South Asian Earthquake" in Equals, Newsletter for Beyond Access: Gender, Education and Development 16, January- March 2006:6. Department for International Development (Dfid), Institute of Education (IOE) and Oxfam.

Book Review: "Rao, N. and Smith, I. (eds.), (2005), <u>Partnerships for Girls' Education</u>, Oxford: OxfamGB", in Equals, Newsletter for Beyond Access: Gender, Education and Development. Issue 11, March/April 2005:7. Department for International Development (Dfid), Institute of Education (IOE) and Oxfam.

CONFERENCES, SEMINARS AND WORKSHOPS

- Organizational Network Analysis Methodology Training and the Capacity Development Market, Hanoi, Vietnam organized by SNV, facilitated by Root Change.
- Workshop on Gender Mainstreaming and Sensitization by UNICEF
- Transforming Teacher Education: Improving Practicum and Internship
- First International Conference on Quality Teacher Education: Promises and Practices
- Canada Pakistan Basic Education Project Workshop on Event Management, Lahore, Pakistan
- Canada Pakistan Basic Education Project Workshop on Quantitative Research Methods Lahore, Pakistan
- International Conference on Women's Empowerment and Social Transformation; Institute of Social and Cultural Studies, University of the Punjab, Lahore, Pakistan
- National Conference on Changing Role of Teachers in the Era of Globalization
- Impact Chain Workshop facilitated by GTZ, Directorate of Staff Development, Lahore
- Exhuming accountability: Conference on Transitional Justice in South Asia; Khatmandu, Nepal,
- Discourses of Differences Within and Beyond Education; Institute of Education, University of London

EDUCATION

Institute of Education (IOE), University of London MA Education, Gender and International Development, 2004-05

Department of Public Administration, the University of Punjab, Lahore, Pakistan Masters in Public Administration, 1997 - 99

VOLUNTEER WORK

Volunteer, Akhtar Hameed Resource Center, June 2010 to date

Volunteer, Akhuwat, January 2008 to date

Volunteer, Garrison Rotary Club, Lahore, November 2006 to date

Volunteer, Al-Sehar Foundation, January 2006 to date

COURSES AND ADDITIONAL QUALIFICATIONS

Sixth South Asian Orientation Course in Human Rights and Peace Studies; Online (May-September 2006)

Six compulsory modules of the course were: Basic Concepts of Human Rights; Constitution, laws and justice; Conflicts and the Politics of Peace; "The Global War on Terror"; Globalization, politics of technology and environmental justice, and Media and Conflict.

AWARDS AND DISTINCTIONS

Rotary International Group Study Exchange Member May – June 2008: Selected by the Rotary International as a member of a team of four for a Group Study Exchange trip for a study tour to Paraguay and Argentina.

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

Board Member for HollaBack! an international NGO dedicated to ending street harassment using mobile technology.

Board Member for JEHAT a local NGO working on capacity building of Community Based Organizations and local NGOs.

Alumni association of the Institute of Education, University of London

British Alumni Association Pakistan (BAAP)

Council of Social Sciences, Pakistan (COSS)

Institute of Administrative Sciences Alumni Association

Pakistan Association for Women Studies (PAWS)

Pakistan Coalition for Education (PCE)

REFERENCES

Available on request